Finding aid to the Zelie De Lussan papers SSC.MS.00045
Sophia Smith Collection
Zelie De Lussan papers
1863-1949
Sophia Smith Collection
De Lussan, Zélie, 1861-1949.
SSC.MS.00045
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Zelie De Lussan was an opera singer. Papers include biographical information; photographs; notebooks; concert programs and scrapbooks, including material from performances before Queen Victoria; correspondence; and posters.
Biographical / Historical
Zélie De Lussan (1863-1949) was born in Brooklyn but lived in London most of her life. She began her career as an opera singer at age 16 in 1889 with the Carl Rosa Company in London. From 1890-1910, she performed in the Royal Opera Covent Garden, and she performed with New York City's Metropolitan Opera, 1895-96. She toured the U.S. with the Metropolitan, circa 1900. In 1907, she married pianist Angelo Ronani. De Lussan performed the role of Carmen "over 500 times," and she was a favorite of Queen Victoria.
Scope and Contents
The Zélie De Lussan papers include biographical information; photographs; notebooks; concert programs and scrapbooks, including material from performances before Queen Victoria; correspondence; and posters.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Helen Calvocoressi Offenhauser. Year unknown.
Opera--England--London; Singers--United States--Biography--Sources; Sopranos (Singers)--United States--Biography--Sources; correspondence; Programs; Notes; scrapbooks; clippings; photographs; memorabilia; Metropolitan Opera (New York, N.Y.)--History--Sources; Royal Opera House (London, England)--History--Sources; De Lussan, Zelie, 1863-1949; Patti, Adelina, 1843-1919; Delibes, Leo, 1836-1891; Offenhauser, Helen Calvocoressi; Kuester, Despina Offenhauser; De Lussan, Zelie
- Contents (Box 1)
- Photos (Box 1)
- Notebooks, 1863-1949 (Box 1)
- Zelie De Lussan to Duke and Duchess of Kent (Thanks), 1934 (Box 1)
- Adelina Patti to Zelie De Lussan, 1887-1890 (Box 1)
- Arthur Goring Thomas to Zelie De Lussan, 1890 (Box 1)
- Programs of concerts, operas (Box 1)
- Performances before Queen Victoria (Box 1)
- French poster (Box 1)
- Letters to Zelie De Lussan, miscellaneous correspondents, 1915-1949 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous mementos, 1888-1921 (Box 1)
- Scrapbook: concerts, 1877-1888 (Box 1)